I'd like you to imagine the world anew.
أودّ منكم تخيل العالم على نحو مغاير.
I'd like to show you some maps,
أود أن أريكم بعض الخرائط
which have been drawn by Ben Hennig,
والتي رسمها (بين هينيغ)،
of the planet in a way
للأرض بطريقة
that most of you will never have seen the planet depicted before.
لم يشاهدها بعد معظمكم عن الأرض المصورة من قبل.
Here's an image that you're very familiar with.
لدينا هنا صورة مألوفة جداً بالنسبة لكم.
I'm old enough that I was actually born before we saw this image.
وفي الحقيقة لقد ولدت قبل مشاهدتنا لهذه الصورة.
Apparently some of my first words were "moona, moona,"
أولى كلماتي التي نطقت بها كانت "مونا، مونا،"
but I think that's my mom having a particular fantasy
ولكنني أعتقد أن لدى أمي خيال خاص
about what her baby boy could see
حول ما يمكن أن يشاهده طفلها الصغير
on the flickering black and white TV screen.
على شاشة التلفاز الأبيض والأسود المتأرجحة.
It's only been a few centuries
إنها عدة قرون فحسب
since we've actually, most of us, thought of our planet as spherical.
منذ أن فكر معظمنا بأن كوكب الأرض كروي.
When we first saw these images in the 1960s,
حين مشاهدتنا لهذه الصور لأول مرة في الستينيات،
the world was changing at an incredible rate.
كان العالم يتغير بسرعة لا تصدق.
In my own little discipline of human geography,
وفي معرفتي الصغيرة حول الجغرافيا البشرية،
a cartographer called Waldo Tobler
فإن رسَام خرائط يدعى (والدو توبلر)
was drawing new maps of the planet,
كان يقوم برسم خرائط جديدة للأرض،
and these maps have now spread,
وقد انتشرت هذه الخرائط الآن،
and I'm going to show you one of them now.
وسأعرض عليكم إحداها الآن.
This map is a map of the world,
هذه خريطة العالم،
but it's a map which looks to you
ولكنها خريطة تبدو بالنسبة اليكم
a little bit strange.
غريبة بعض الشيء.
It's a map in which we stretched places,
إنها خريطة مددنا فيها الأماكن،
so that those areas which contain many people are drawn larger,
لذلك رسمت المناطق التي تضم عدداً أكبر من السكان بحجم أكبر.
and those areas, like the Sahara and the Himalayas,
وتلك المناطق كالصحراء الكبرى والهيميلايا،
in which there are few people, have been shrunk away.
حيث يتواجد عدد قليل من البشر قُلصت للغاية.
Everybody on the planet is given an equal amount of space.
حيث أعطي كل شخص على سطح الكوكب مساحة متساوية.
The cities are shown shining bright.
وتبدو المدن متلألأة.
The lines are showing you submarine cables and trade routes.
وتظهر الخطوط الكابلات تحت سطح البحر والطرق التجارية.
And there's one particular line that goes from the Chinese port of Dalian
وهناك خط خاص من مرفأ (داليان) الصيني
through past Singapore,
إلى جانب سنغافورة،
through the Suez Canal,
وعبر قناة (السويس)
through the Mediterranean and round to Rotterdam.
وعبر البحر المتوسط ليلتف حتى روتردام
And it's showing you the route
ويظهر لكم الطريق
of what was the world's largest ship just a year ago,
لما كان أكبر السفن في العالم منذ عام مضى فحسب،
a ship which was taking so many containers of goods
وهي الباخرة التي كانت تأخذ العديد من حاويات البضائع
that when they were unloaded,
والتي كانت إذا فُرِغّت،
if the lorries had all gone in convoy, they would have been 100 kilometers long.
وسارت الشاحنات جميعها في قافلة لكانت ستكون بطول 100 كيلومتر.
This is how our world is now connected.
هذا ما هو عليه عالمنا اليوم.
This is the quantity of stuff we are now moving around the world,
هذه هي كميات المواد التي نقوم بشحنها الآن حول العالم،
just on one ship, on one voyage,
فقط في باخرة واحدة، ورحلة واحدة،
in five weeks.
في خمسة أسابيع.
We've lived in cities for a very long time,
لقد كنا نعيش في مدن لمدة طويلة من الزمن.
but most of us didn't live in cities.
ولكن معظمنا لم يعش في مدن.
This is Çatalhöyük, one of the world's first cities.
هذه كاتالويوك أحد أوائل المدن في العالم
At its peak 9,000 years ago,
وفي فترة ازدهارها منذ 9000 عام،
people had to walk over the roofs of others' houses to get to their home.
كان على الناس المشي فوق سطوح المنازل الأخرى للوصول إلى منازلهم.
If you look carefully at the map of the city,
إذا ما نظرت بتمعن إلى خريطة المدينة،
you'll see it has no streets,
سترى أنه لم تكن هنالك أية شوارع،
because streets are something we invented.
إذ أن الشوارع هي أمر اخترعناه.
The world changes.
إن العالم يتغير.
It changes by trial and error.
ويتغير عبر المحاولات والأخطاء.
We work out slowly and gradually
ونحن نعمل إما ببطئ أو بالتدريج
how to live in better ways.
كي نحيا في عالم أفضل.
And the world has changed incredibly quickly most recently.
ومؤخراً، تغير العالم بسرعة لا تصدق.
It's only within the last six, seven, or eight generations
حدث ذلك في غضون الأجيال الستة أو السبعة أو الثمانية الماضية
that we have actually realized that we are a species.
حتى أدركنا أننا أنواع.
It's only within the last few decades
وفي العقود القليلة الماضية
that a map like this could be drawn.
أصبح بالإمكان رسم مثل هذه الخريطة.
Again, the underlying map is the map of world population,
ومرة أخرى، الخريطة المشار إليها هي خريطة لتعداد سكان العالم،
but over it, you're seeing arrows showing how we spread out of Africa
ولكن فوقها تشاهدون أقواساً تظهر كيفية انتشارنا خارج أفريقيا
with dates showing you where we think we arrived
مع التواريخ التي تظهر لكم أين نعتقد أننا وصلنا
at particular times.
في أوقات معينة.
I have to redraw this map every few months,
علي أن أعيد رسم هذه الخريطة كل عدة أشهر،
because somebody makes a discovery that a particular date was wrong.
لأن شخصاً ما يكتشف أن تاريخاً معيناً كان خاطئاً.
We are learning about ourselves at an incredible speed.
إننا نتعلم عن أنفسنا بسرعة لا تصدق.
And we're changing.
ونحن نتغير.
A lot of change is gradual.
الكثير من التغيير تدريجي.
It's accretion.
إنه ازدياد.
We don't notice the change
نحن لا نلاحظ التغيير
because we only have short lives,
لأننا نحيا حياة قصيرة،
70, 80, if you're lucky 90 years.
70 أو 80 وإن كنت محظوظاً قد تبلغ التسعين.
This graph is showing you
يظهر لكم هذا الرسم البياني
the annual rate of population growth in the world.
المعدل السنوي لازدياد عدد السكان في العالم
It was very low until around about 1850,
فقد كان منخفضاً جداً حتى عام 1850،
and then the rate of population growth
وبعدها معدل نمو السكان
began to rise
بدأ بالازدياد
so that around the time I was born,
وكان ذلك في الوقت الذي ولدت فيه،
when we first saw those images from the moon of our planet,
حين شاهدنا للمرة الأولى هذه الصور المأخوذة لقمر كوكبنا.
our global population was growing at two percent a year.
كان عدد السكان في العالم يزداد بنسبة 2% سنوياً.
If it had carried on growing at two percent a year
ولو أنه تابع الازدياد بنسبة 2% سنوياً
for just another couple of centuries,
فقط على مدار قرنين آخرين،
the entire planet would be covered
فإن الكوكب بأكمله سيكون مغطى
with a seething mass of human bodies
بكتلة عارمة من الأجساد البشرية
all touching each other.
تلامس بعضها بعضاً.
And people were scared.
ولكان كل الناس خائفين.
They were scared of population growth
كانوا سيخشون من النمو السكاني
and what they called "the population bomb" in 1968.
وما أطلقوا عليه اسم "القنبلة السكانية" في العام 1968.
But then, if you look at the end of the graph,
ثم إنه، إذا ما نظرت إلى نهاية الرسم البياني،
the growth began to slow.
فإن النمو يبدأ بالتباطؤ.
The decade --
العقد --
the '70s, the '80s, the '90s, the noughties,
السبعينيات والثمانينيات والتسعينيات،
and in this decade, even faster --
وفي هذا العقد، وعلى نحو أسرع --
our population growth is slowing.
إن معدل نمونا السكاني يتباطأ.
Our planet is stabilizing.
كوكبنا يستقر.
We are heading towards nine, 10, or 11 billion people
نحن نقترب من 9 أو 10 أو11 مليار نسمة
by the end of the century.
بنهاية القرن.
Within that change, you can see tumult.
وبهذا التغيير سنشاهد الشغب.
You can see the Second World War.
حينها ستشهد الحرب العالمية الثانية.
You can see the pandemic in 1918 from influenza.
وستشهد مثل وباء الإنفلونزا في عام 1918.
You can see the great Chinese famine.
وستشهد المجاعة الكبرى في الصين.
These are the events we tend to concentrate on.
هذه هي الأحداث التي نميل للتركيز عليها.
We tend to concentrate on the terrible events in the news.
نميل للتركيز على أحداث الأخبار المريعة.
We don't tend to concentrate on the gradual change
فنحن لا نميل للتركيز على التغيير التدريجي
and the good news stories.
وقصص الأخبار الجيدة.
We worry about people.
نحن نقلق على البشر.
We worry about how many people there are.
ونحن قلقون حول عدد الناس الموجودين.
We worry about how you can get away from people.
نحن نهتم بكيف لك أن تبتعد عن الناس.
But this is the map of the world changed again to make area large,
ولكن خريطة العالم هذه تغيرت ثانية لتجعل الأماكن أكبر،
the further away people are from each area.
والبشر من كل منطقة أبعد عن بعضهم.
So if you want to know where to go to get away from everybody,
لذا إذا أردت معرفة أين عليك الذهاب لتبتعد عن الجميع،
here's the best places to go.
هذه هي الأماكن الأفضل لذلك.
And every year, these areas get bigger,
وكل عام، ستصبح هذه المناطق أكبر،
because every year, we are coming off the land globally.
إذ أنه كل عام نبتعد عن الأرض عالمياً.
We are moving into the cities.
فنحن ننتقل إلى داخل المدن.
We are packing in more densely.
ونغدو أكثر كثافة.
There are wolves again in Europe,
هناك ذئاب مجدداً في أوروبا،
and the wolves are moving west across the continent.
وتتحرك الذئاب غرباً عبر القارة.
Our world is changing.
عالمنا يتغير.
You have worries.
وتعتريكم المخاوف.
This is a map showing where the water falls on our planet.
وتظهر هذه الخريطة أماكن هطول الأمطار على كوكبنا.
We now know that.
فنحن نعرف ذلك الآن.
And you can look at where Çatalhöyük was,
وبإمكانكم معرفة أين كانت (شاتاهويوك)،
where three continents meet, Africa, Asia, and Europe,
حيث تلتقي القارات الثلاث أفريقيا وآسيا وأوروبا،
and you can see there are a large number of people living there
وبإمكانكم أن تروا أن العديد من البشر يحيون هناك
in areas with very little water.
في مناطق تقل فيها المياه.
And you can see areas in which there is a great deal of rainfall as well.
وبإمكانكم أن تروا مناطق تهطل فيها الأمطار بغزارة أيضاً.
And we can get a bit more sophisticated.
وقد يعترينا مزيد من الرضا.
Instead of making the map be shaped by people,
فبدلاً من أن تكون الخريطة من صنع البشر،
we can shape the map by water,
لندع الماء يرسمها،
and then we can change it every month
وبالتالي بإمكاننا تغييرها شهرياً
to show the amount of water
لنظهر كميات الماء
falling on every small part of the globe.
التي تسقط على كل جزء صغير من العالم.
And you see the monsoons moving around the planet,
وكذلك ترون الرياح الموسمية تنتقل عبر الكوكب،
and the planet almost appears to have a heartbeat.
ويبدو العالم وكأن لديه دقات قلب.
And all of this only became possible
وأصبح كل ذلك ممكناً
within my lifetime
أثناء حياتي
to see this is where we are living.
لنشاهد المكان الذي نعيش فيه.
We have enough water.
لدينا ماء كافٍ.
This is a map of where we grow our food in the world.
هذه خريطة للأماكن التي نزرع فيها غذاءنا في العالم.
This is the areas that we will rely on most for rice and maize and corn.
هذه المناطق التي سوف نعتمد عليها غالباً في الأرز والذرة والقمح.
People worry that there won't be enough food, but we know,
يشعر البشر بالقلق حيال نقص الغذاء، لكننا نعلم،
if we just ate less meat and fed less of the crops to animals,
أننا إذا تناولنا لحوماً أقل وأطعمنا الحيوانات محاصيل أقل،
there is enough food for everybody
سيكون هناك ما يكفي الجميع
as long as we think of ourselves as one group of people.
طالما نفكر بأنفسنا كمجموعة واحدة من البشر.
And we also know
ونعلم أيضاً
about what we do
أن ما نفعله
so terribly badly nowadays.
مريع للغاية هذه الأيام.
You will have seen this map of the world before.
فقد تكون قد رأيت خريطة العالم هذه من قبل.
This is the map
هذه هي الخريطة
produced by taking satellite images,
الناتجة عن صور التقطتها الأقمار الصناعية،
if you remember those satellites around the planet
إذا كنت تذكر تلك الأقمار الصناعية التي تدور حول الأرض
in the very first slide I showed,
في الشريحة الأولى التي عرضتها،
and producing an image of what the Earth looks like at night.
ومعطية صورة عن الهيئة التي تبدو عليها الأرض ليلاً.
When you normally see that map,
حين ترى هذه الخريطة عادةً،
on a normal map, the kind of map that most of you will be used to,
على خريطة عادية، من ذاك النوع الذي اعتاده معظمكم،
you think you are seeing a map of where people live.
فقد تعتقد أنك ترى خريطة للأماكن التي يحيا عليها البشر.
Where the lights are shining up is where people live.
فحيث تتلألأ الأضواء يحيا البشر.
But here, on this image of the world,
ولكن هنا، في خريطة العالم هذه،
remember we've stretched the map again.
تذكّر أنّنا وسعنا الخريطة ثانية.
Everywhere has the same density of people on this map.
كل مكان لديه الكثافة السكانية نفسها على هذه الخريطة.
If an area doesn't have people,
وإذا لم يكن بمنطقة ما بشر،
we've shrunk it away
قمنا بتقليصها
to make it disappear.
لتبدو غير مرئية.
So we're showing everybody
وبالتالي فنحن نظهر الجميع
with equal prominence.
بنفس الأهمية.
Now, the lights no longer show you where people are,
والآن، لا تظهر لكم الأضواء بعد الآن المكان الذي يحيا فيه البشر،
because people are everywhere.
لأن البشر في كل مكان.
Now the lights on the map,
الآن الأضواء التي على الخريطة
the lights in London, the lights in Cairo, the lights in Tokyo,
أضواء لندن والقاهرة وطوكيو.
the lights on the Eastern Seaboard of the United States,
الأضواء على الساحل الشرقي للولايات المتحدة
the lights show you where people live
تظهر لكم الأضواء المكان الذي يحيا به البشر
who are so profligate with energy
نحن شديدو التبذير في الطاقة
that they can afford
والتي يمكنهم تأمينها
to spend money
لصرف الأموال
powering lights to shine up into the sky,
على إشعال الأنوار لإضاءة السماء،
so satellites can draw an image like this.
كي تتمكن الأقمار الصناعية من رسم صورة كهذه.
And the areas that are dark on the map
والمناطق المعتمة على الخريطة
are either areas where people do not have access to that much energy,
فهي إما مناطق لا يستطيع قاطنوها الوصول للطاقة المتاحة فيها،
or areas where people do,
أو مناطق يستطيع سكانها ذلك،
but they have learned to stop shining the light up into the sky.
ولكنهم تعلّموا ألا يبذروا الطاقة بلا جدوى.
And if I could show you this map animated over time,
وإذا ما أتيح لي أن أعرض عليكم هذه الخريطة المتحركة مع الزمن،
you would see that Tokyo has actually become darker,
سترون أن طوكيو غدت أكثر عتمة مع الزمن،
because ever since the tsunami in Japan,
إذ أنه ومنذ التسونامي في اليابان،
Japan has had to rely on a quarter less electricity
توجب على اليابان الاعتماد على أقل من ربع الكهرباء
because it turned the nuclear power stations off.
لأنها أغلقت محطة توليد الطاقة النووية.
And the world didn't end.
ولم ينته العالم.
You just shone less light
إذ أنك فحسب أنرت أنواراً أقل
up into the sky.
لتشع إلى السماء.
There are a huge number
هناك أعداد كبيرة
of good news stories in the world.
من الأخبار الجيدة في العالم.
Infant mortality is falling
فوفيات الأطفال في تناقص
and has been falling at an incredible rate.
وما زالت في تناقص بمعدلات لا تصدق.
A few years ago,
منذ عدة أعوام،
the number of babies dying in their first year of life in the world
انخفض عدد الاطفال الذين يلقون حتفهم في عامهم الأول في العالم
fell by five percent in just one year.
بمقدار 5% في عام واحد فقط.
More children are going to school
والمزيد من الأطفال يرتادون المدارس
and learning to read and write
ويتعلمون الكتابة والقراءة
and getting connected to the Internet
وأصبح لديهم اتصال بالإنترنت
and going on to go to university
وفي طريقهم ليرتادوا الجامعات
than ever before at an incredible rate,
بمعدلات أكبر مما سبق،
and the highest number of young people going to university in the world
والأعداد الأكبر من الشباب الذين يرتادون الجامعات في العالم
are women, not men.
هم من النساء وليس الرجال.
I can give you good news story after good news story
فبإمكاني إعطاؤكم القصة الجيدة تلو الأخرى
about what is getting better in the planet,
حول ما أصبح أفضل في كوكبنا،
but we tend to concentrate
ولكننا نميل للتركيز
on the bad news that is immediate.
على الأخبار السيئة الفورية.
Rebecca Solnit, I think, put it brilliantly,
(ريبيكا سولينت)، على ما أعتقد قالتها بوضوح،
when she explained: "The accretion of incremental, imperceptible changes
حين شرحت: " التزايد التدريجي والتغيرات المحسوسة
which can constitute progress and which render our era
والتي يمكن أن تؤسس لتقدّم عصرنا
dramatically different from the past" --
تختلف تماماً عن الماضي" --
the past was much more stable --
كان الماضي أكثر استقراراً بكثير --
"a contrast obscured by the undramatic nature of gradual transformation,
"وهو النقيض الذي حجبته الطبيعة غير التامة للتحول التدريجي،
punctuated by occasional tumult."
والتي تتخللها أحيانا الاضطرابات"
Occasionally, terrible things happen.
وتحدث عرضياً أمور فظيعة.
You are shown those terrible things
ويتم عرض هذه الأمور عليك
on the news every night of the week.
في الأخبار كل ليلة طول الأسبوع.
You are not told about the population slowing down.
لم يخبرك أحد عن انخفاض النمو السكاني.
You are not told about the world becoming more connected.
لم يخبرك أحد عن العالم الذي أصبح متصلاً على نحو أكبر.
You are not told about the incredible improvements in understanding.
ولم تُخبر بالتطور الشديد في الفهم.
You are not told about how we are learning to begin
ولم تُخبر كيف أننا نتعلم
to waste less and consume less.
أن نبذر أقل ونستهلك أقل.
This is my last map.
هذه هي خريطتي الأخيرة.
On this map, we have taken the seas
في هذه الخريطة، استبعدنا البحار
and the oceans out.
والمحيطات.
Now you are just looking
أنت الآن تنظر فقط
at about 7.4 billion people
إلى 7.4 مليار نسمة
with the map drawn in proportion to those people.
في هذه الخريطة التي رُسمت بالتناسب مع هؤلاء البشر
You're looking at over a billion in China,
أنت تنظر إلى مايفوق المليار في الصين،
and you can see the largest city in the world in China,
بإمكانك أن ترى أن أكبر مدن العالم هي الصين،
but you do not know its name.
ولكنك لا تعرف اسمها.
You can see that India
بإمكانك أن ترى أن الهند
is in the center of this world.
في وسط العالم.
You can see that Europe is on the edge.
بإمكانك أن ترى أوروبا على الحافة.
And we in Exeter today
اليوم نحن في (إكستر)
are on the far edge of the planet.
في الطرف القصي من العالم.
We are on a tiny scrap of rock
نحن على قطعة صغيرة من صخرة
off Europe
خارج أوروبا
which contains less than one percent
تضم أقل من 1%
of the world's adults,
من البالغين في العالم،
and less than half a percent
وأقل من 0.5%
of the world's children.
من أطفال العالم.
We are living in a stabilizing world, an urbanizing world,
نحن نحيا في عالم مستقر، عالم متمدّن،
an aging world,
عالم يتقدم في السن،
a connecting world.
عالم متصل.
There are many, many things to be frightened about,
هنالك الكثير مما علينا أن نخشى حياله،
but there is no need for us to fear each other as much as we do,
ولكننا لسنا بحاجة أن ننقل مخاوفنا إلى الآخرين،
and we need to see that we are now living in a new world.
نحن بحاجة لأن نرى أننا نحيا في عالم جديد.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)